[Música]
[Aplausos]
muchas gracias
es un gran placer estar aquí una vez
nuevamente en buenos aires
y en muchas ocasiones he estado en argentina
y he celebrado el software libre con
ustedes
mi charla de hoy es una charla muy especial
porque este es un año muy especial
son 50 años desde 1969
y en 1969 hubo muchos
eventos interesantes
número uno la gente caminó sobre la luna
y el planeta entero se detuvo
dieciséis
ese día
mientras la gente corría hacia todos los televisores
de el mundo
para ver a la gente más asombrosa
y se unieron en todo el mundo
por este concepto de gente caminando
en un cuerpo diferente en el espacio
algo menos importante pero aun asi
importante era woodstock
un festival de música gigante en los estados unidos
estados para establecer el tono de la música
durante las próximas décadas
en 1969 en la ciudad de nueva york
hubo un motín en un lugar llamado el
stonewall inn
donde las personas trans estaban siendo
intimidadas y heridas y gente gay y
personas de diferentes tipos de diversidad
estaban siendo perseguidas por la policía
y causaron un motín que inició el
comienzo de la comunidad y movimiento lgbtq
en los
estados unidos
en un pequeño laboratorio en bell labs en
New Jersey
dos personas iniciaron una pequeño sistema
operativo
solo por diversión, ellos no pensaron que era
va a ser importante
solo estaban tratando de hacer una investigación
en nuevas ideas de sistemas operativos y
ver un poco más sobre eso
en esta charla Arpanet
fue fundado y eventualmente se convirtió en el
Internet
y la gente nunca soñó que el
Internet sería lo que es hoy
de hecho, el espacio de direcciones del
Arpanet original
eran solo 15 bits
por lo que no podría tener muchos hosts
en Helsinki finlandia paso desapercibido
salvo
para los padres de Linus Torvalds, porque fue el año del nacimiento de
Linus
si Linus Torvalds tiene 50 años
este año que me hace sentir increíblemente
viejo
en 1969 yo era un estudiante universitario
sesenta y cinco
como muchos de ustedes yo estaba estudiando
Ingeniería Eléctrica
y la mitad de mi carrera fue en negocios
y administración
Casi fui electrocutado por 13600
voltios y 800 amperios
lo que casi me guió hacia el software
y programación
finalmente en 1969 fue el último año
en el que me he
afeitado, ahora notarías un poco
asterisco al lado de eso
lo que indica a lo largo de mi charla
que hay otra historia detrás de eso
pero no tenemos tiempo para todos esos
cuentos
pero más asteriscos hay, más
largo y a veces mejor la historia es
y si me invitas a salir con una birra
a veces puede ser que te las cuente
pero, vamos a volver al
principio, no demasiado al principio de
la ciencia de la computación
pero cuando empece a programar
y la computadoras eran físicamente inmensas
trabaje para una compañía llamada Aetna Life
and casualty(?)
y eran los usuarios comerciales mas grandes
de equipamiento de IBM en el mundo libre
que te va a mostrar que si pones suficientes
adjetivos alrededor vos, vos podrías ser el
mejor de cualquier cosa
soy el el hombre mas guapo con
barba blanca
y pelo parado en este escenario en este
podio, ves? soy el mejor
pero las computadoras eran también lógicamente muy
chicas
tendrían capaz 4000 bytes de
memoria
y trabajarían con dispositivos que
podrían
leer y escribir datos a cinco caracteres
cinco bytes por segundo
esto era medido en megabytes no
gigabytes o terabytes
como hacemos hoy y los programas
corrían
una vuelta a la vez en la computadora aun si
la computadora era un mainframe
y aun si costaba 2.5 millones de dolares
los programas eran corridos de a uno a la vez
y, y muchas de estas computadoras tenían
switches
y luces en el frente de ellas porque
vos podías usar esos switches
y luces para depurar tu programa
porque tu programa era la única cosa
que estaba corriendo
y si había un sistema operativo, era
increíblemente primitivo
para los standards de hoy era típicamente
especializado en hacer un tipo de cosa
tal vez podrías hacer un trabajo por lotes en las tarjetas
o quizás si tenias realmente suerte, you
had a time
sharing system that would you could have
terminals attached to
there were computers that were dedicated
to real-time processes
and there was there's a rumor and it's
still a thought pattern today
that companies created different
operating systems because they were
trying to
lock their customers into their hardware
they were trying to get their customers
to write to that
operating system because that would tie
that customer to their equipment
now if this was true then the digital
pdp-11
computer system that was very popular in
the day
would only need to have one operating
system
but instead we had 11 different
operating systems
because what we were trying to do was
make that piece of hardware
be more efficient in running our
customers programs
and so we wrote the operating system
to do specialized tasks we had an
operating system for doing
health style of work and an operating
system for doing
educational style of work and an
operating system for doing real-time
style of work and so forth and so on
we actually had two different unix
systems
running on our pdp 11.
and if we were just trying to lock our
customers into buying our equipment
we would need only one
now also back in those days most
of the code that was distributed was
distributed in source code form
there wasn't enough of one type of
computer
to really justify creating a binary
code and manufacturing it like cookie
cutters
and so if you ordered a compiler
you might spend one hundred thousand
dollars
for that compiler and you might
negotiate with the company for several
months with your lawyers talking to
their lawyers
about how many systems could you put
that compiler on
and how many people could use it at one
time
and in the end you ended up
with the source code for that compiler
you kept that
in your vault or in your lawyer's vault
because what happens if that little
company that you bought it from goes out
of business
there were also very few professional
programmers
there were there weren't people who
really wrote programs for other people
to use
and if you were a programmer it was
because you were also a physicist
and you needed the program to do your
work you were an electrical engineer
work
you're an educator and you needed the
program to do your work
in fact i had a professor at the
university drexel
who said to me john you'll never be able
to
earn a living being a professional
programmer
and i'm still waiting to see if he was
right
there were also no software copyrights
or patents
you could not copyright software you
could not patent software
the way you protected your software was
to
contract law making one of these
contracts
and getting people to sign it and this
required much money and many lawyers
even before you
touched the software and there was also
many points of sharing
there were vendors groups like dekus for
the digital equipment user society
share for ibm brainstorm for novell
where people who wrote these programs
would contribute their programs in
source code form
to people to use
and and why did they do this why didn't
they sell
their software well quite frankly
selling software is hard work
you have to guarantee bug fixes to your
software you have to write documentation
for your software
you have to distribute your software all
these different things
and the people that wrote this software
were not
in the business of selling software
they were physicists and engineers and
educators
so they gave away their software to
other people who they thought could use
it
and sometimes these people would meet
them
at these meetings like decas and say oh
you wrote that great software i'm using
thank you very much it's very helpful
i have some ideas to how to make it
better or
gee you wrote that software that really
saved my life
let me buy you a beer
or they did a really great job let me
buy you dinner
well you did a really great job let me
give you a job
and these a lot of these reasons are the
same reasons that people write free
software today
they write it because they need it for
themselves
and they write it because they can
demonstrate
their programming skills and a lot of
times get a job
or generate a service out of writing it
now i've described the computing
industry
in 1969 but
this one guy named ken thompson had been
working on a project called baltics
there was a combination of different
companies coming together
and trying to create a be all end-all
operating system
called baltics and eventually ken
thompson was taken off of this project
and brought back to bell labs in new
jersey
and he was very upset about this because
he liked
working on operating systems and he met
up with this other man named dennis
ritchie
and together they started to create this
little operating system that they called
unix because baltics was everything for
everybody
and unix was one thing for one person
and they started by saying well instead
of putting all the functionality
in the center of the computing system
called the kernel
let's make the kernel very small and
have it do
some things very well and then all the
other things that people need will move
outside of the kernel
into these things called libraries
and this made it easier to get that
kernel
to be correct now the first couple of
kernels were written in the ones and
zeroes
of machine language but after a while
dennis richie said boy this is really
difficult
um i'm going to invent this language
called c
and we'll rewrite the kernel in c and
then it'll be much more
portable to the next system we bring it
to
and they kept working on this to make it
more and more
portable now this was a
strange thing in those days because
computers were so expensive
that who cares if you have to train your
person to use a different operating
system
to be more efficient for running your
program
because the machine was worth more than
the people were
and dennis and ken had this idea
that people were actually more expensive
than the machines were and as the cost
of the machine started to drop
this became more and more true
that it became easier and easier to buy
a new machine with the same
operating system on it and the same
commands
and the same libraries maybe a different
machine
architecture but that was hidden from
you by the operating system
and people found out that i can use the
same programs and the same command
whether the machine comes from
hewlett-packard or ibm or compaq
or any number of other companies that
are no longer in existence
and at first this this operating system
was distributed in source code form
and this allowed universities to
participate in bringing good
ideas into this a collaborative effort
and ken and dennis would bring in some
ideas and toss away others and things
like that they were the architects of
the system
but despite the fact that a lot of
people think that unix was free
it was never free it was always owned by
a t and t
and sometimes it was barely even open
because only universities that were
researched universities
could get the code for a reasonable
price
350 u.s dollars to put the code on
all of the computers at your university
if you were a small two-year technical
college
like the one i taught at you had to get
a different license
and that license was 160 000
us dollars per cpu
and you had to tell somebody at the
telephone company
the serial number of the computer you
were putting it on
now how many of you have ever tried to
call somebody at the telephone company
it's like trying to call somebody at
google
do you know in the 150 million pages
that google is in charge of
web pages there's not a single telephone
number
you can't call people at google you can
barely send them email
so this concept that unix was free and
open was
a myth
these remember these guys were creating
this operating system
just for fun they were researchers
they didn't mean to sell this or
anything they wanted just wanted people
to use it
and other contributions from unix
systems
was a small command interpreter which we
call the shell
it still exists today even in linux a
lot of you use the shell you call it
bash
well this show was called the bourne
shell
it was written by a man named steve
bourne and it was simply
sh later on there was another shell
written
that extended that at the university of
california berkeley
and it used the c syntax so it was
called
csh and then another
show was written by a man named dave
cord it extended that
and it was called the corn shell ksh
and so forth and so on eventually the
free software foundation
wrote to shell over again making it free
software
they called it the born again shell
bash which a lot of you use today
but this was a new concept normally
all this functionality was in the kernel
of the operating system
which made the kernel bigger and more
complex and more likely to fail
one of the great features of unix and
the unix command line is something
called pipes and filters
which allows you to take the output from
one command and feed it into the input
of the next command
this is this was another new concept and
it was so new
that the person who invented it named
doug mcelroy
had to actually write some of the first
unix commands
to show ken thomps ken thompson and
dennis ritchie
how this worked things like portable
network
file systems came from unix and a client
server windowing system was developed at
mit
for unix systems and there were many
more
very radical ideas that came out of the
unix
marketplace now
all of these unix systems were being
developed by universities
and the universities would pass around
the source code
but if but the source code was still
very expensive
if you were a company you'd had to pay
two hundred sixty thousand dollars
and so what happened in 1962
was a little company called sun
microsystems
had formulated a small computer
that was built and designed to stanford
university
and they said we want to have a
powerful operating system on top of this
little computer
ms-dos was too weak and miserable
for this system cpm another operating
system of the day
was only good for 64 bits of
i'm sorry um 16 bits of address space
various 65 000 bytes of memory so
both of these were just too weak
sun actually came to my company digital
equipment corporation and said we want
to
take one of your operating systems but
that was impossible
so they decided to use
the university of california berkeley's
version of unix
which is called bsd and
they wanted to go to the telephone
company and say can we have
a better license a cheaper license for
this
and the telephone companies said okay if
you distribute unix
only in binary form not the source code
you can sell it for three hundred fifty
dollars per machine
and you do not have to tell us what the
serial number is
and sun microsystems said wonderful
we'll do that
now you have to remember that even
though this was a small
desktop computer it was still selling
for fifteen
thousand dollars back in 1982.
that's about half the price that my
parents paid for their house
a three-bedroom house with brick
it had a living room a dining room a
family room a two-car garage
one a quarter acre of land they paid 32
000 for it so this workstation
that sat on your desk and allowed you to
do work
was half the price of their house
but people still paid it because it
allowed them to do amazing work
and they put this unix license on top
now other companies like digital
equipment corporation and
hewlett-packard
and ibm saw the business model and they
too
started to bring out their own versions
of unix
also in binary only form
not in the source code
but most of them utilize the code from
the university of california berkeley
and the reason for that is that the att
code called system 5 was
a swapping type of operating system
it meant that you had to have your
entire program
in memory at one time the berkeley
system used something called demand page
virtual memory
which meant you only had to have a
certain portion
of your program in memory at one time
this was more desirable
system five only had two compilers that
came with it
c and fortran 77.
the berkeley code had three compilers
they added pascal
but the most important thing was the
system five networking
was a dial up networking called unix to
unix copy
where your computer system would
actually dial up over the telephone
lines
make a connection to the next system and
pass the data on
and the berkeley system had implemented
tcpip
[Music]
remember tcpip it came from the internet
that was started in 1969
but one thing that the university of
california did not have
that system five did was a big marketing
budget
and so for the next 10 years every week
in the middle of this big computer
magazine a t
would have an advertisement for system 5
the right
choice but nevertheless they still
lost now there was one person who
objected
to this binary only copy of
unix he was a student at mit
in in boston
and he decided that he liked seeing the
source code for these operating systems
it was worthwhile having it it made it
easier to maintain the operating system
his name of course was richard stallman
and he announced this project called gnu
a project to completely rewrite
all of unix in source code and make it
freely
available and the first
piece of code he wrote was emacs
a text editor now emacs is so complex
that most people say he could have
stopped with emacs and he would have had
his complete operating system
but he went on to do other programs that
were useful to programmers
and these programs would work on
different
operating systems so you could use emacs
on
mvs and vms and unix systems
and so forth and all of a sudden
programmers got the idea
got the information that yes i only have
to learn my text editor
one time and i can use it on
all these other different systems
and the next thing he did was write some
compilers
that worked on all these different
systems
and people start to say well i can write
my code the same way
on all these systems and the only thing
i have to watch out for
are the system calls to the actual
operating system itself and he started
to gather more and more people that saw
this vision
and in 1985 he created the free software
foundation
which i bear the brand on his shoulder
[Applause]
[Music]
now he kept doing this you know
first the emacs and then the compiler
suite and then
various utilities and people began to
understand
that this was allowing people to be
portable across these different
operating systems
and this also allowed some small
companies to start up
giving support to this software that was
written by the free software foundation
some of them simply gathered up the
source code
and put them onto cd-roms and sold the
cd-roms
other people actually printed books
about how to use this software
and o'reilly is one of the major book
manufacturers that did that
and some companies like a company called
cygnus
actually supplied support to major
corporations like boeing
to use these compilers on different
systems
they did some work specifically paid for
by these companies that the free
software foundation
didn't have access to the machines or
the people
to do it and so people started realizing
that you can make money by supporting
free software
now the company i worked for digital
equipment corporation
we had been supporting unix from the
telephone
company from bell labs on our deck
hardware
but we were mostly writing device
drivers and things like that
and i joined digital in 1983.
i'm going to stop here for a moment and
i realized that most of you were not
born at that time
some of you your fathers were not born
at that time
but i joined in 1983 and
uh we were bringing out a unix system
based on 4.1
berkeley software distribution we bought
out two of them one of them was a
32-bit a 16-bit system called ultrix 11
and one was a 32-bit system called
ultrix 32.
now this started these unix wars
as different vendors started to see that
there was this market
that could be satisfied with unix mostly
it was a scientific and technical market
and software development market and
educational market
that was about 16 percent of the
marketplace
the other 84 of the marketplace
was what we call commercial software
which is represented by
banks and you know commerce and things
like that
that was still in the mainframe and
batch and proprietary operating system
area
databases were also you know in that
and they typically ran on commercial
systems
so there were two groups that formed one
was called unix system labs
which was made up of sun microsystems
and a tnt
that joined together and the sun did a
very stupid thing
they decided to abandon the code from
the university of california berkeley
and instead support the code from system
of bell laboratories this was a decision
made by upper management
for political reasons and the engineers
looked at the code from
a t and said this is terrible
and so the very first release of their
new code base was called
slolaris because it was so slow
compared to sun os their bsd base
eventually they did the optimization to
bring it up to speed
the other companies like dec ibm and
others
formed a group called the open software
foundation
and what they did was create a set of
standard
programming interfaces and a test suite
and a set of standards to say if you can
pass these standards
then you can call yourself unix
this was a radical idea because it meant
that you could
implement an operating system using
any code base you wanted to
as long as the programming interfaces
stayed the same and it also meant
that the most important thing was the
brand
of the product unix
it allowed people to know what they were
getting
now this started some wars companies
vying back and forth
and eventually in 1991
unix system labs sued a tiny little
company called bsdi
and said you're using a t
code without paying royalties to the
telephone company
and bsdi said no no the code that we get
is all from the university of california
berkeley
and the telephone company said no
there's still some you know a telephone
code
in there and this dragged on for years
and this stopped people from moving
forward
with the bsd code as a solution
to a free operating system
eventually
the bsdi people and the university of
california berkeley
got rid of all of the atnt
code at that point they created a
distribution called bsd lite
that became the basis of certain
operating systems that still exist today
in the open source space netbsd
freebsd and openbsd
but that was 1994.
in 1991 there was
a student named
lena's torvalds at the university of
helsinki and he had gotten a brand new
386 computer
for christmas and the 386
computer had a facility to it a feature
to it
that no other intel system had before
and that system that feature was to be
able to run
demand page virtual memory
remember the importance of that
from where unix came from years before
lenas knew that his system had that
capability but the operating system
that came with it from a company
named microsoft did not take advantage
of that feature because microsoft
was still supporting the customers using
the 186
and the 286 that did not have this
feature
so lenas decided he was going to write a
kernel
that used this feature and this would be
his operating system he was writing it
for himself just for fun
and he sent out a message over the
internet he said i'm writing this
operating syst just for fun
it's not going to be as big and powerful
as medics
and people started joining him with that
and giving their expertise and their
time to help to generate this kernel
which would then be the core of the
operating system that some people call
gdu linux now
why could this happen at this time
why at this time why not before when not
after
is because there were these cheap
powerful computers
and the 386 was not new in 1991
it was actually a several years old
and people had older 386 computers
lying around their house that they could
say oh
i can dedicate this computer to this
linux project
and there was also faster internet to
the house
both dial up and dsl and cable
which allowed people to do this work at
home
not having to do the work at the
university or doing the work at their
employment
there was a lot of information online
about how to build operating systems
there was the minix model
of building operating systems and there
were other toy
or other operating systems that were
done that people could see
the techniques of using them and in 1989
the world wide web had been invented
and was now maturing to make it easier
to transfer
huge amounts of data with links
to make this production easier
and even porn was easier
back because of the world wide web
so in 1994 which were three years after
lena started his curdle project and
ten years after the gnu project was
created
people brought together the linux kernel
and various parts of the lytic system
to create the gnu linux system
now at that time system vendors
except for sun had given up the desktop
computer to microsoft
and microsoft owned ninety percent of
the desktop market
with apple owning seven percent and
everything else
owning three percent windows nt
had been invented by by microsoft it was
not only
it's used in some desktops but also
using server systems and this was
scaring
the large vendors because this is where
they used unix
and this is where they used their
proprietary systems
and microsoft was eating into that space
tim o'reilly had actually stopped
producing books on unix because he said
it was a dying market
and he was actually producing books
about windows and tea
i don't blame him he had people that
were working for him
he had to keep them with jobs so
i don't really blame him for for
deserting the unix market
but in 1994
venus had finished version 1.0 of the
linux kernel
and had released it now when you create
operating systems
a version anything less than version one
is still
a heavily developing model it's not
really
ready for everybody to use version one
is the signal to people
that this is an operating system that
you can use
now i met lenas at a deacos meeting
in new orleans in 1994 and the reason
that new orleans
has two asterisks behind it is that
there are two cities in the united
states which are
adult disneylands one of them
is las vegas the other is new orleans
and i love new orleans
and i met linus and i saw linux for the
first time
and i sat down and i used linux and i
said wow this is really good
this is not this is on a weak miserable
crappy intel computer chip
it isn't a vax it isn't an alpha this is
one of these weak
miserable crappy intel chips and this
felt really good it was really peppy
this was something really good
and i said to lena's linus would you
like to create a 64-bit version
of linux because the alpha was a 64-bit
computer
why is that important with 32 bits you
can access
4 billion bytes of data at one time
but with 64 bits you can access 4
billion
times four billion bytes of data
how much data is that
that will fill up a one gigabyte disk
every second of the day
every day of the year for the next 5
386 years
or it'll allow you to store 128 bytes of
data
for every square millimeter on the
surface of the earth
including all the oceans it's a lot
of data and
it allows him to support multiple
processes not just intel and amd
but alpha and motorola and arm
and all the rest that were coming and he
said yes
he'd be happy to do that so i gave him a
thirty thousand dollar computer system
and i got some engineers from digital to
help him
and then i began to understand the power
of the free and open source community
the people who took their own money to
go out and buy alpha processors
so they could help with this project of
pointing linux
to the 64-bit system and in nine
months we did a port
a port where most of the people never
met each other face to face they
only worked over the internet
and i had engineers at digital
who told me that this was impossible
and at that point the new linux exploded
and it wasn't just gnu linux but it was
software from
all these different places came together
from mit
from from bsd from other from carnegie
mellon from
all these different places and but the
operating system still had no real
applications
no commercial applications but what was
happening
was the world wide web remember that
and the world wide web needed server
systems
that were had shells and it had
a web server and it had email services
and all these things were
on unix and now got put it to linux
and it was on these weak miserable
crappy but cheap
intel systems that people started to put
into place
as routers as firewalls
they started reusing old equipment that
could no longer run microsoft
to do all these things at no
additional expense
several other things happened in rapid
succession 1994 where beowulf
supercomputers came into being we'll
talk more about those in a moment
in 1998 databases like informix and
cybase and oracle
all ported to unix systems or linux
systems
and that meant something to me because
this was exactly the same
set of procedures and steps
that other operating systems took as
they
started to gain momentum
in the year 2000 embedded systems chose
linux as being the
most used system for embedded system
designs
up until this point embedded systems
were
specific operating systems written by
people
but in the year 2000 customers started
saying
we want our embedded systems to talk
to the internet oh my god
that means they have to be secure
and they have to have a tcp stack oh
that's difficult
oh my god what are we going to do
there's an operating system
that already runs on all these
processors it already has a tcp stack
it already is secure and it's called
linux
and it's free
and overnight people started using linux
for new embedded system designs
i mentioned super computers in 1994
supercomputers were very expensive but
the companies that made them were dying
companies like ecl cray
control data corporation
and you would design one of these
systems and only four people would buy
them
sometimes they were government agency
that we dare not say their name
we dare not talk about the nsa
and some a couple universities would
take it but universities never pay you
for anything
because they don't have any money so you
might actually sell one of them
and that just wasn't enough to keep you
alive
so the companies were dying and these
two people
donald becker and dr thomas sterling
said
we need supercomputers because of
one very very special problem
you may not even think about it's a
problem called
fluid dynamics
you know i tell people that math is
behind
everything math is behind physics and
physics is behind the real world
well fluid dynamics is the essence of
math and physics
fluid dynamics is everything it is the
air it is the water it's the currents in
the water
is the weather it is this piece of wood
maybe the wood is a solid but the heat
flow through this wood
is fluid and so this is a very
hard problem to solve very compute
intensive we used to build wind tunnels
to test airplanes and to test
cars for aerodynamics they were very
expensive to build
but you could simulate that if you had
enough computing power
and you wouldn't have to build this very
expensive
wind tunnel and so
they said we can take this gigantic hard
to solve problem and break it down into
many many
tiny little problems and instead of
having a supercomputer do it
we'll use these weak miserable crappy
intel pcs
to solve each tiny little problem and
then bring the answers together
and they called this the beowulf
supercomputer
now this was developed in 1994
inadvertently
i met a young man in 1995 who was going
to university
i said here's a copy of red hat linux
all you read people out there i gave
them red hat linux
and overnight all the national
laboratories in the united states used
red hat linux to build their beowulf
supercomputers
that is actually a copy of the young man
i gave that cd to
his name is pakgoda and he's in front of
a system called loki
which pat was using to what to simulate
what would happen
if meteors crashed into the earth
up until 2001 he was crashing them into
new york city
after september the 11th he chose los
angeles
but he still went on okay and today
of the 5 000 fat or sorry the 500
fastest computers in the world
all of them run linux
the same linux that you run on your
laptop
or your desktop
two of them used to run micro used to
run microsoft because microsoft paid
them to run microsoft
we can't have all 500 running linux
you know pay them to run microsoft but
it got too expensive
they're still there but they're like 572
of you know the 500 fastest computers
you see they're a prize the gordon bell
prize
gordon bell works for the microsoft
corporation
in their supercomputer area they're
named after him given to the best
supercomputer
it's never been won by microsoft
i know gordon he's a great guy
so the next thing that happened was the
years of the unix desktop
and actually let's just say linux
desktop but
you know unix we kept trying to get it
onto the desktop
and people would not use unix because
they were too used to ms-dos and windows
i don't know if you remember this but
your parents
when you said use the computer system
they would write down in the notebook
hit this button wait to the screen
lights up
type in this name type in this word
that's your password
and they would write this down in a
notebook because that's the way they use
computers
and that's one reason why people did not
switch over to using linux on the
desktop because they were too used to
using computers that way
from this one standard interface or what
they thought was standard
microsoft another reason for
not using the new linux was the lack of
games
now games is an interesting subject
here in argentina you actually pirate
about 84 percent of your desktop
software
yes you laugh and clap
but what happens when it's your program
that you have written and you are
expecting to make money
off of the software that you wrote
you're expecting to feed
your family you're expecting to be able
to make your tuition to go to school
is it so funny then
this is one reason why i as a free
software person
are is adamant against software and
privacy
because it takes money out of the mouths
of people
who expected to make write that money
write that software and make money from
it
instead you should be using truly free
software software written with the
intent
of giving it away and the intent of
having you
help make it better a collaborative
development model
but with games it's even worse because
the piracy rate of games is 99
the game company makes the one cd and
magically that cd is duplicated 50 000
times yeah we
we bought the one copy and this is why a
lot of game companies are now
giving away the game software and
selling you plastic toys instead or
making you attack attached to a server
and pay
a subscription fee because that's the
only way that they can make money
this is why when people say to me how do
i make money with free software i say to
them
the very first thing you do is you write
a business plan to make sure
that after you've done the work of
creating this free software that you
have a way
of making money to keep the free
software going
but the other reason why linux doesn't
really make it on a desktop
is the fact that most people need only
five applications
they really do they need a desktop
application
they need all this stuff and they never
get to that
i am told i'm out of time so i'm going
to skip ahead a little bit
another threat is apple where apple
decided that computers weren't computers
anymore they were actually consumer
items
they wanted you to buy an iphone because
it was
fancy and because you could brag to your
friends
not because it necessarily did anything
you wanted
it to do but android
foiled apple's plan because remember
there used to be ninety percent
microsoft and seven percent
apple microsoft took the philosophy if
you could even say the word windows
you could put your software on their
hardware
and apple said nobody will make money
from us
unless they're named apple
android screwed up apple's plan
because android is now the new microsoft
if you could even say the word android
you can have your application there
you can put android on top of your
hardware
so all these hardware vendors are
creating different platforms
for people to use
and now we have the cloud the cloud is
another way
that people can these companies can trap
people
into using their facility i come from
this company
in this country called the united states
you may have heard of us
and the united states has this law
called the constitution
which protects my privacy against
these agencies which i've mentioned
but you have no privacy in my country
you have no rights under my law none
zero
zip and so if your data even creeps
across
our borders or goes through certain
places that are controlled by us
my country can look at your data with
impunity
if i entered into the conversation they
have to stop
because i'm a u.s citizen but as long as
you're talking to yourselves you're
talking to other people in other
countries
they can listen and they can change your
data if they want to
this is why it's important for you to
make
way to store your most important data
inside of your country
and you have to understand what happens
when that data escapes
your control you need
we have to take back the cloud from the
large cloud vendors
i'm going to skip the summary of the
history what i'd like to do
is talk about the future for a bit
we have users these days people that
don't know about computers people have
never written the program
but they're using computers we have to
make them
understand about freedom
we have to make them understand that the
opposite of freedom is slavery
companies tell you what to do when to go
where to put the code
what you can do with it when you have to
retire it
when you have to upgrade that is
software slavery
and when you're a slave you have no
control
you have no control over your life
you're told when to marry when to have
children when to die
you are a slave
and we don't want that because we are
human beings
some companies say they love open source
in the ancient greek there were three
words for love one was agape
the love of god for man the love of
mother for
child but even a mother's child the
mother's love
is not without cost if you love me
you'll take out the garbage
if you love me you'll feed the dog
but it is the greatest of love
the second love is filos brotherly love
from that we give philanthropy in
philadelphia and psychology
philadelphia the city of brotherly love
the love of you for your friends
not quite agape but then there's the
third love
errors the deepest
dirtiest love sexual love
we get erotic from that erotica
sex that is the love
that some companies have for free
software
and open source do not bend over in the
shower
we are very close to world domination 60
of all the servers in the world run
linux the 500 fastest computers in the
world run linux
most embedded systems your d-link
routers your elderly
elsa's routers either run linux or bsd
we are very
all of the major companies in the world
run free software in some way
shape or form you just have to go
a little bit further and that's your job
your job is to publicize free software
is to publicize why it's good is to make
people understand that with free
software they
have control
i'm still working on a series of
projects but quite frankly
i'm 69. my brother retired at 55
most people i know retired is 65 i've
had three heart attacks
but i am working on a few projects like
caninus lucas which was shown down in
the stand for these last three days
these are computers that we are
designing and building in brazil
and i'm here in argentina to help you
start designing the same type of
computers here
i've made some good contacts we're going
to share ideas
and we're gonna start building these
computers in latin america instead of
sending
billions and trillions of pesos to china
i have nothing against china i have a
lot of chinese friends
but they make enough money and i want to
create jobs in argentina
and i want to create jobs in latin
america
and there's things like internet of
things which are too dangerous
to allow this to be done by people
outside of your country
we need to have software freedom
for them finally
thank you
i have one last retirement project
mad dogs monastery and marina
of math music microcomputing
micro brewing micro winery
micro distillery and bait shop
because if you have a marina you need a
bait shop
this is opening in 2025 and you're all
welcome
and one last thought people have been
coming up to me
the whole week and saying thank you very
much for coming to argentina
thank you for the work you do but i tell
you
that if you want to see the most
important person
in free and open source software and
hardware
when you get up tomorrow morning you
look in the mirror
because it's you thank you very much
[Music]
[Applause]
alien
bye